RG 157, Commission on Forfeited Rights
Connecticut State Library
Commission on Forfeited Rights records
1949-1975
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Commission on Forfeited Rights
20.25 cubic feet
Established in 1949 and abolished in 1975, the Commission on Forfeited Rights was charged with the responsibility of reviewing and acting upon petitions to restore forfeited electoral rights for those who had been released from prison.
RG157
1984-112
Historical Note
Prior to 1949, the General Assembly reviewed all petitions for restoration of electoral rights forfeited by persons convicted of various offenses. The process was criticized because (a) the legislature met once every two years, (b) petitioners received undesirable publicity, and (c) the influx of petitions increased the assembly's workload. In 1948 voters approved an amendment to Section 3 of Article VI of the State Constitution and Article XVII of the amendments thereto, directing the General Assembly to "prescribe the offense on the conviction of which the privileges of an elector shall be forfeited and the conditions on which and methods by which rights" were to be restored. The General Assembly responded by creating the Commission on Forfeited Rights (Public Act 350, 1949 Supplement to the General Statutes, Revised 1959, Revised 1964, Sections 9-46 to 9-49).
The Commission consisted of three members, appointed in each odd-numbered year for two-year terms. The Governor appointed an elector, the Speaker of the House appointed a member of that body, and the President Pro Tempore appointed a member from the Senate. The law prohibited any active judges of the Supreme Court, any Superior Court or Court of Common Pleas or any State Referee from serving on the Commission.
The General Assembly directed that the Commission meet once quarterly at the county court house in Hartford or any other county court house in order to hold hearings on petitions. Meetings were closed to the public. Commission members also met with pre-release inmates at the Connecticut Correctional Institution at Somers to inform them of procedures for regaining voting rights. The Assembly empowered the Commission to summon witnesses, to issue subpoenas, to have access to records of prosecuting attorneys, to make its own regulations regarding hearings, and to make decisions from which there were no appeals.
Public Act 350 also made provisions for the process. Petitioners (or friends or family members) filed affidavits giving information about the conviction and sentence, a complete criminal history, and current address and occupation or employment of the petitioner. The Commission could not hear any petition until six months after release of the petitioner from a correctional facility or after discharge from parole or probation. The Commission could request that the State Police investigate and report on any petitioner prior to hearings. The law directed the Commission to inform petitioners, their friends and relatives, chief executives of towns, boroughs, or cities of residence, and state's attorneys or prosecuting attorneys of courts of original jurisdiction of impending hearings.
Majority vote was required by law for approval of any petition. The Commission informed appropriate local registrars of voters of every approved petition. Petitioners, where applications were rejected, had the right to rehearing six months after the original decision.
In 1945 the General Assembly considered a bill to abolish the Commission (see Public Act 354). Critics of the Commission, including the Secretary of the State charged that procedures deterred potential candidates from petitioning and cited figures showing that since 1949, the Commission had received only 2,100 petitions out of a potential total of 46,000. The legislature abolished the Commission effective June 30, 1975 and provided fro automatic restoration of voting rights upon submission of evidence to registrars of voters in the locality of a petitioner's residence at time of conviction of discharge from incarceration, probation, or parole.
See also the.
Scope and Content
Series 1. Minutes of Meetings include records of meetings, quarterly reports, reports about prison visits, press releases, newspaper clippings, transcript of hearing on P.A. 354. Series 2. Sound Recordings consist of five inch diameter discs, most of which are marked with names and dates of petitioners. The cover about half the number of petitions. They may be dictaphone recordings of hearings. However, equipment to hear recordings is not available. Series 3. Petitioners Case Files contain files of applicants whose petitions were approved. Files contain affidavit from petitioner, two letters of character references, hearing transcripts, correspondence relating to hearings, final decisions. Series 4. is Administrative Subject Files.
Arrangement
Arranged into four series: Minutes that are arranged chronologically; Sound recordings are unarranged; Petitioner case files are arranged alphabetically by petitioner last name; Administrative subject files arranged alphabetically.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. Commission on Forfeited Rights
Subjects:
Connecticut. Commission on Forfeited Rights -- Records and correspondence; Ex-convicts -- Suffrage -- Connecticut; Political rights, Loss of -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Correspondence; Minutes; Reports; Sound recordings
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
The records of the Commission were discovered in May, 1984 in the State Capitol basement and were accessioned in that month into the State Archives. In the initial arrangement, useless financial records relating largely to application fees were weeded out.
Container List
- Series 1. Minutes of meetings, 1951-1975
  - 1951-1973 (Box 1)
  - 1973-1975 (Box 2)
- Series 2. Sound recordings, 1956-1970
  - Sound recordings, 1956-1970; approximately 600 discs (Box 2)
    Unarranged.
    Equipment to hear recordings is not available.
- Series 3. Petitioner case files, 1949-1975
  - Abascol - Asplund (Box 2a)
  - Asuntino - Bicknell (Box 3)
  - Bike - Brundage (Box 4)
  - Brunetti - Cattaneo (Box 5)
  - Caulkins - Convertito (Box 6)
  - Cooper - DeFeo (Box 7)
  - DeFeo - Diorio (Box 8)
  - D"Iorio - Ersoff (Box 9)
  - Esposito - Frost (Box 10)
  - Funari - Grasso (Box 11)
  - Gnutti - Guzman (Box 12)
  - Hackley - Howell (Box 13)
  - Huard - Kartovsky (Box 14)
  - Karwosky - Kulenski (Box 15)
  - Kurz - Levine (Box 16)
  - Levitan - McLaughlin (Box 17)
  - McMinn - Mazziot (Box 18)
  - Medina - Morrone (Box 19)
  - Morse - Orsini (Box 20)
  - Pacileo - Picozzi (Box 21)
  - Pilato - Richardson (Box 22)
  - Riccitelli - Salit (Box 23)
  - Sampana - Shay (Box 24)
  - Shea - Speziale (Box 25)
  - Spiotti - Tetro (Box 26)
  - Theroux - Volinsky (Box 27)
  - Wacha - Winning (Box 28)
  - Wisnewski - Zygmont (Box 29)
  - Applications rejected (Box 29)
  - Applications rejected (Box 30)
  - Incomplete applications (Box 30)
  - Incomplete applications (Box 31)
- Series 4. Administrative subject files, 1949-1975
  - Advice of allotment, 1970-1971 (Box 32)
  - Aeronautics Dept. correspondence, 1959 (Box 32)
  - Annual reports, 1953-1972 (Box 32)
  - Applications sent out, 1956-1964 (Box 32)
  - Applications sent out, 1964-1971 (Box 33)
  - Attorney General correspondence, 1962-1974 (Box 34)
  - Attorney General - Federal rulings and correspondence, 1954-1963 (Box 34)
  - Attorney General - Rulings and opinions, 1955-1975 (Box 34)
  - Auditor's reports, 1952-1970 (Box 34)
  - Auditor's request fro confirmation, 1950-1971 (Box 34)
  - Bill 27/1965 constitution (Box 34)
  - Bills - Forfeited Rights Commission, 1964-1975 (Box 34)
  - Budget Division (correspondence), 1963-1970 (Box 35)
  - Budget Report Governors, 1961-1972 (Box 35)
  - Civil Defense, 1956-1968 (Box 35)
  - Commission on Forfeited Rights (Box 35)
  - Commissioners appointments, 1955-1973 (Box 35)
  - Comptroller's Dept. correspondence, 1968-1975 (Box 35)
  - Comptroller's Dept. correspondence, 1968-1975 (Box 36)
  - Contributions, 1956-1974 (Box 36)
  - Copy of cases heard in New Haven conspiracy trial, 1952 (Box 36)
  - Correspondence Consumer Protective Office, 1971 (Box 36)
  - Correspondence - General, 1956-1957 (Box 36)
  - Correspondence - General, 1957-1970 (Box 37)
  - Correspondence - General, 1972-1975 (Box 38)
  - Court Clerks, correspondence to deposits, recording fees (Box 38)
  - Federal Correctional Institution, Danbury, Conn. - correspondence from (Box 38)
  - Finance and Control Dept., correspondence, 1956-1972 (Box 38)
  - Finance & Control - Monthly personnel status report (Box 38)
  - Firearms Permit Examining Board (Box 38)
  - Forfeited Rights - formation of, 1947-1949 (Box 39)
  - Farms - hearings in Absentia (Box 39)
  - Function & position (Box 39)
  - Governor's Office - communications from (Box 39)
  - Health, State Dept. of (Box 39)
  - Highway Department (Box 39)
  - Human Rights Commission (Box 39)
  - Insurance - coverage fro state employees (Box 39)
  - Legislative Commissioner - correspondence from - S.B. 288 (Box 39)
  - Legislative Management correspondence (Box 39)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 39)
  - Notices sent to Commissioners, 1971-1975 (Box 39)
  - Personnel (Box 40)
  - Personnel, 1974-1975 (Box 40)
  - Public Act 350 - Establishment of Commission on Forfeited Rights and Public Act 382 (Box 40)
  - Public Works Department (Box 40)
  - Purchasing Department (Box 40)
  - Recording fees, 1949-1951 (Box 40)
  - Records management (Box 40)
  - Regain your right to vote (Box 40)
  - Registrar of Voters (Box 40)
  - Restoration of Rights - notices for (Box 40)
  - Retirement Commission (Box 40)
  - Secretary of State (Box 40)
  - State Employee Retirement Act (Box 40)
  - State of Conn. - constitution (Box 40)
  - State Prison, Wethersfield - correspondence (Box 40)
  - Surety Bond (Box 40)
  - Treasurer, Office of (Box 40)